[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet resume of
holography
hello and welcome to the season finale
of whole talk
for the final show of the season I
thought it would be a nice idea to look
back and highlight many of the shows
that were broadcast this season
for the summer months I will replay
these shows in their entirety for those
listeners who either never had the
chance to hear them originally and for
those who would like to listen again
talk will return with a new season of
shows on September 13th right after
Labor Day
to start off I spoke with Paul Graham of
light vision early in the season and
asked him if he could share the
technique of putting holograms on edible
foods in this particular case lollipops
here's what he had to say
without giving any secrets out that you
obviously have to hold on for your own
protection of doing this and inventing
this technology with you know your
company
could you tell some of the listeners
what goes into putting a holographic
image on a lollipop
um yes I can um well basically the
history of the Hologram was that it was
invented by a physicist at MIT his
name's Eric bakladder and Eric is
actually a principal of our company uh
he actually still handles all the
holography work for us Erica discovered
that he could impart images on the food
products so basically what he devised
was a system where he can cut little
tiny grooves in the surface of the food
what happens is the light comes in and
reflects off these grooves and forms an
image in your eye just just the way
things happen was sort of like an
embossed hologram basically it's a very
similar sort of process
you're able to do this with Pops I
believe because something to do with the
sucrose or something being almost like a
plastic yeah basically I mean basically
moist food most Foods
flower starches and sugars
I really thought natural form of plastic
I mean they're not as stable form but
they effectively work like a plastic I
mean glasses as you know with embossed
Holograms performing glass is actually
also also sort of like a plastic type
agent so Eric sort of postulated that he
could use food similar to uh using
metals or glass or anything else and it
tends to work
on another show Wang Hunter Chun of
holographic Development Corporation in
Shenzhen China told holotalk listeners
how holography is currently used in
China
how are Holograms used in China are they
used in magazines or packaging the
Hologram in China commonly used only for
the label on some small package I see
that's that's what we can see anywhere I
think uh in U.S and the other countries
it's also you know like some inbox
labels yes that takes almost 99 in China
and usually they are very small they are
wine to two centimeter squares yes I can
find some bigger ones in abroad but in
China it's only small ones actually we
never say any other use like in the
magazine cover or books or any any
package the in the package they have
some not hologram they have some a shiny
materials like a hologram papers
we took a virtual trip up the Victoria
British Columbia and visited the
holography shop of Derek gallon he told
us about his Russian holograms on
exhibit at Royal holographic Gallery
Frank we tried to have as much as uh as
possible of different artists on a
different Hall run products we try to
find a new product we constantly search
for them that's the reason we are able
to show a quite unique Russian programs
we started the partnership with Russian
holograph three years ago we have a
constant display of our Russian
holography
made mostly on a Russian glass plate
which is kind of difficult for sitting
but they are extremely high quality as
you know and they're very interesting so
we have like a one wall devoted only to
Russian holography most of it is like a
Russian artifacts from our museums but
there is a few modern art pieces
quite a interesting display I would say
uh the other
Holograms we have are Larry Lieberman
multipolar hologram we have some other
Holograms from Holland
from that holography studio
and we have the photopolymers which are
huge
made once using very well-known Masters
from Mrs awesome as well as Mr Terry so
they are quite a good on another show
Alex Simons of three deep company gave
us some technical information on making
the switch from AG for holographic
recording materials to the new slavage
materials
um for my group of people and I mostly
get amateurs in Educational Services and
things of that nature at the site that's
the majority of people that come through
the site but I imagine they would be
interested in two types of the emotions
the PFG batch zero one and the
pfd-03m that's true that's what I would
guess so the helium neon users yes now I
I received the package from slavish this
week and it does say p f g-01 is good
for laser transmission and reflection
holography is that true well there's uh
there's two old one there's a pfg01
which is As I understood it to be
transmission
laser or helium neon and then there's an
o1m which is a slight Improvement it
doesn't have an anti-hale um halation
backing and it's for transmission and
reflection I see and it has a greater
it's actually a faster Emulsion than the
O3 that's right it is a faster Emulsion
okay because I've got some of ags's
older information here from their AE 75
HD emulsions
and it appears to me that it may be
possible to make reflection Holograms
with this said
Dash zero one uh Emulsion yeah but there
one the analog zero one would be the
8075 and the o1m the analog would be an
8 e75 HD uh the o1ms are not uh that we
don't have them yet they won't arrive
until mid-January
but at the moment we're we're reducing
our buys of the 01 that's straight for
transmission because it looks like the
o1m is really going to support just
about everybody's needs if there's our
if there are special needs requiring the
older the type Emulsion of course we'd
be happy to pick that up on the next uh
restocking Dr Stephen Benton of the
media lab at MIT filled holotalk
listeners in on the latest advances in
holographic technology here we spoke on
compressing holographic video well I
think the internet has made the person
on the street very well aware of
compression Technologies how do
compression Technologies figure into
this scheme of holography is it an
important aspect
well uh and certainly in holographic
video uh we're uh you know we're we're
making these little Holograms about
three inches by five inches inside size
size that that take 36 megabytes each of
of raw hologram data that's not very
much actually is it well you know it's
not as much as it used to be this audio
file will take up more space than that
when we're finished yeah uh so uh but
it's still it takes a while to pump 36
megabytes across from any place to any
place uh if you especially if you're
trying to do 30 of them a second yeah so
uh so we've been looking at compression
techniques
um you know we've gotten up to about 32
to one uh with uh pretty visually
lossless uh compression that's uh
techniques that are designed around the
specific properties of of diffractive
images
Mark lucente who graduated from here a
couple years ago did a lot of work on
what he called diffraction specific
computing
or compression and
we we're going to need that stuff when
if we try to ship a holographic video
images moving images over any very long
distances but
did you see the Men in Black video
colors at the store Brian Monahan from
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper talked with
us about how his company created them on
this holotalk show excellent now you had
a couple interesting projects one of the
ones that goes back a little ways Star
Trek generations yeah and then you've
got the Men in Black video covers uh
video cassette cover as well yeah that's
awesome we'll talk about that
actually the Star Trek one was the good
that you know we won uh we won a few
Awards with the ihma the international
hologram manufacturer's Association for
the Star Trek box he he and it really in
my opinion turned out turned out really
pretty fantastic it achieved its goal
um the that led into a lot of other
projects some smaller ones but then
eventually into the Men in Black which
last year definitely if not to date was
the largest holographic packaging job in
the world
Alan Rhodey from Ross books talked about
a very exciting development at Sony this
show generated the most listeners and
emails of any other show
basically Sony just unveiled the first
uh fully portable
portrait hard ethics diagram portrait
printing system by portable our idea of
portable sometimes means like a Walkman
right and it is something like that no
kidding can be used Outdoors it's
basically uh you sit in front of a
scanning digital camera that's on a rail
and the rail is about three four feet
long the camera travels down the rail it
takes
225 separate images
that it feeds into an image Processing
Unit you know just through a wire okay
and the image processing unit is located
in a box about the size of the desktop
copying machine wow it goes through the
image process or the Mr processor takes
all the different Parallax views and
regenerates
295 different views left to right
sends them into
an Optics board located on a little
isolation platform built into this thing
get out and the uh the condensed images
or well actually the images are shown on
a an LCD screen it's a spatial light
modulator valve they call it and it's
condensed into a vertical strip onto a
diffusion diffuser screen
and then it's recorded with a little
green laser a solid state laser directly
on a piece of DuPont photopolymer
Mr X who wanted to remain anonymous
spoke about his extensive collection of
holograms and also spoke about
holographic philosophy and David Bohm
now I know you follow a lot of different
things with holography including some of
the theories of Dr David Bohm and some
of the other people that uh
well when he was alive he was the
professor of theoretical physics and uh
he had some really
um unique ideas about you know the
relationship between Holograms and the
universe and how possibly the cosmos the
holographic in nature and uh that was
really interesting talking to him and
discussing philosophy with him it was a
really good book if people would be
interested that deals with uh some of
his ideas and with Holograms and that
kind of a thing and it's fairly simple
you know in terms of reading it's called
glass Universe okay and uh f David Pete
and uh John Briggs are the author okay
this is a Looking Glass Universe Looking
Glass universe and a couple other titles
they may want to look into is uh
wholeness in the implicit order yeah
I think he did that maybe in conjunction
with the Christian Marty right yeah
krishnamurti is a philosopher he passed
away also but some of his uh
ideas I'm really appreciative of too
because he deals a lot with holistic
aspects of things and how The Observers
he observed
I asked Dr Jay Young from Lake Forest
College about the hottest future
applications of holography and he gave
his thoughts on this and some advice for
students as well
at the kitchen and holography in the
next 10 years is computer memory yes
holographic Optical element for control
light inside the computer chip to feel
good information from one chip to
another via light
that's the important news even now the
most important uses of holography uh you
know in the Palm pymat I always wear
cheap watches because I lose them when
I'm one thing
but there's a hologram in in there that
you're looking right through
really I used to when you push the
button at night to look at what time it
is there would be one little bright
light on one corner and spread out to
the other side and it say it's out
right now there's a hologram layer in
there that's expressed the light evenly
throughout the entire space of my watch
it's a hologram nobody knows about that
I did not know about that on the Timex
watch yep in the Motorola uh cell phone
you put it on at night there's a
hologram on the on under the Glass isn't
that interesting in other words they're
in lots of places in a CD player there's
a hologram inside to split the light
send the light to different places you
know and grocery store and in other
words Holograms are already in many
places people don't know and in the
future it'll be many other places
that's something and that's whole area
so I tell students they can have fun
making Holograms of pictures to learn
maybe that's their profession make art
image artistic images but by learning
one thing you automatically are learning
a million tanks you will be late you
know one learning to another how generic
learnings are that one physical law
applies to infinite number of things
ever try to do holography during an
earthquake Steve province of Blue Ridge
holographics fill this in on why they
moved from the west coast to the East
Coast
we've been pretty fortunate uh it was
just minor stuff some clean benches
crashed and HEPA filters got poked
through and stuff and stuff like that
but it wasn't those events that actually
spooked us from uh you know working in
Quake country it was the bloody
aftershocks
because a lot of the shots we do record
uh you know seven or eight different
elements or channels all done in a
sequence yeah you know tightly
registered sequence and all of a sudden
one out of seven
for no
explainable reason the shot wouldn't
come out yeah now photoresist as as you
may know is is a very slow uh very
insensitive animal so it pushes exposure
times up into the minutes range instead
of the seconds range
and frankly after you'd spent you know
six hours getting through a sequence of
13 individual recordings
a single plate
only to find that one of them dropped
out because some
remember you couldn't even feel had
mucked it up you'd have to start all
over and after having to do every job
two or three times
lucky enough to avoid a myth we just
sort of said you know this is
counterproductive
so we loaded up the truck and we moved
it from Beverly
lasers in airspace was just one of the
topics of discussion with L Michael
Roberts of laser FX International he
explained what the news is all about
from what I understand there's a Hot
Topic in Las Vegas right now with well
actually between the laser light show
people and the airport authorities that
are you aware of this oh yes this has
been a very hot issue in the industry
and continues to be a heart issue in the
industry life is in airspace how
came about is that a number of Las Vegas
hotels installed very large laser shows
to shoot beams of light into the sky as
part of attracting people to their
facilities
and in part this year's day new
technology called the yag laser which is
an infrared laser that's been frequency
doubled to 532 nanometers the 532
spectral line is is very very close to
the peak sensitivity of the human eye so
for example a 10 watt Jag laser would
appear as bright to the human eye as the
30 or 35 watt argon laser so some of
these places installed 30 and 40 watt
and some even brighter than that and
multiple of these lasers and shot them
out into the night sky and they did it
all in compliance with existing
regulations but a number of Pilots got
flashed as they were coming into land
and there's a perception amongst a lot
of people that lasers sort of like death
Rays yes and that if you touch it your
face will melt like the guy in in
writers of the Lost Ark but in actual
fact the real danger is that you get
momentary flash blindness in other words
it's very similar to the effect of
having your photograph taken at a dimly
lit party where you sort of see that
after Imaging startled just the flash of
light the largest Holograms ever created
was the topic of discussion with Dr John
Perry of holographics North
big Holograms means big tables and he
told us about his
if I remember correctly from a story I
read about your company maybe in Holy
Spirit back in the things I would think
you actually work on a floor instead of
a table right the floor itself is
isolated from vibration did you pour
like a large concrete floor or something
that's right we we call it a table but
we step right onto it I mean it's that
floor level uh frankly our landlord at
the time insisted on this he wouldn't
let us pour a concrete slab three feet
above the floor it's 12 by 22 feet and
it's 14 inches thick that's a lot of
concrete
and one of the advantages to Flora level
is of course you can just step right on
and walk around you don't have to climb
up climb down we have more Headroom over
it of course by doing that also but
another Advantage more practically is
that someday if somebody puts that room
their uses all I have to do is tile the
tile the table basically and it's a
floor again
um the concrete has reinforcement and
it's not steel it's fiberglass
reinforcement we basically dug a huge
hole
on the ground and uh and filled it up
with snow which we have plenty of here
and then poured the concrete on top of
the snow and with a little blue board in
between to keep the heat
the heat curing from from melting the
snow too fast and then by the time the
snow was melting out the concrete had
set enough to support itself there are
four legs that that hold the whole thing
up and a fairly complicated structure
actually underneath that kind of
supports all that concrete and that all
fits on Piers that go down through
sleeves uh 15 inch diameter sleeves they
could add about 14 feet
and they're anchored directly into the
glacial kill is really what it is um
deep under the building Jason sapan of
holographic studios in New York City
explained the holotalk listeners exactly
what goes into making computer generated
integral Holograms
do you have an automated process or do
you work the machine that yourself is
automated however I would say that as
you know you know the concept of
Automation and holography it's an
oxymoron 99 of the work is you know just
manual and physical and almost
debilitating at times when it comes to
computer transfer in my case I am not
using a liquid Crystal to project the
images off the computer rather I am
transferring the files into a gif viewer
projecting them on my computer monitor
screen transferring them to Motion
Picture film one frame at a time and
then running the motion picture through
the uh holographic printer I have
downstairs in the laboratory here and
that is automated in that you know it'll
Advance one frame of movie film The
holographic film will move an increment
and then the shutter will open uh it'll
close it'll wait for a settling time
it'll then Advance the frame of movie
film and this is as tedious as can be
we're talking many hours at work only to
find out that somewhere you've carted
off an edge of the molecule in this
particular case and you have to start
over and do it all again
so there you have it folks as you know
whole talk has guests every other week
so that was just half of what Hollow
talk listeners enjoyed during this past
season I look forward to returning in
the fall with great new programs and
guests and hope that you'll all be
listening when whole talk returns
September 13th to a computer near you
it was an honor to be your host for the
first year of broadcast
have a happy and safe summer and I'll be
seeing you in the fall take care